and okay
okay
so it's um
55:21 um to Mahanama
um to Mahanama
I've heard that on one occasion the
blessed one was staying among the
Sakians near Capilavatu in Negroes Park
then Mahanama the Sakyan went to the
blessed one and on arrival having bowed
down to him said to one side as he was
sitting there he said Lord this couple
Atu uh is rich and prosperous, populous
and crowded. It is congested. Sometimes
when I enter Kaplawatu in the evening
after visiting the blessed one or with
the monks who inspired the mind, I meet
up with a runaway elephant,
a runaway horse, a runaway chariot, a
runaway cart or a runaway person. At
times like that, my mindfulness um with
regard to the blessed one gets muddled.
My mindfulness with regard to the dhamma
and the sana gets muddled.
The thought occurs to me, if I were to
die at this moment, what would be my
destination? What would be my future
course? Then um the Buddha replies, "Have no
Then um the Buddha replies, "Have no
fear, Mahanama. Have no fear. Your death
will not be a bad one. Your demise will
not be bad. If one's mind has long been
nurtured with conviction, with virtue,
with learning, with relinquishment,
with discernment, then when the body
endowed with a form composed of the four
primary elements, born from mother and
father, nourish nourished with rice and
porridge, subject to inconstancy,
rubbing, pressing, dissolution, and
dispersion, is eaten by crows, vultures, hawks,
is eaten by crows, vultures, hawks,
dogs, hyenas, or all sorts of creatures.
Nevertheless, the mind long nurtured
with conviction, nurtured with virtue,
learning relinchment and discernment,
rises upward and separates out.
Suppose a man were to throw a jar or
ghee or a jar of oil into a deep lake of
water where it would break. There the
shards and jar fragments would go down
while the ghee and oil would rise upward
and separate out. In the same way, if
one's mind has long been nurtured with
conviction, with virtue, with learning,
with relinquishment, with discernment,
then when the body breaks down and is
eaten by crows, vultures, hulks, dogs,
hyenas, nevertheless, the mind will rise
upward and separate out.
So then the repeats, have no fear,
Mahanama, your death will not be a bad
one. And then in Sanguta um 55:22 the next
And then in Sanguta um 55:22 the next
one it's the same story
um and same concern from Muanama and
then um the Buddha tells him that same
have no fear Mahanama have no fear your
death will not be a bad one your demise
will not be bad a disciple of the noble
ones when endowed with four qualities
leans towards nibbana slants towards
nibbana inclines towards nibbana which
four there is a case when the disciple
of the noble ones is endowed with
verified confidence in the awakened one.
Indeed, the blessed one is worthy and
rightly self-awakened, consumate in
knowledge and conduct, well gone and
expert with regard to the world,
unexelled as a trainer for those people
fit to be tamed. Teacher of divine and
human beings awakened and blessed.
He's endowed with verified confidence in
the dharma. The dharma is well expounded
by the blessed one. It's to be seen here
and now. It's timeless inviting
verification pertinent to be realized by
the wise for themselves.
He's endowed with u with a verified
confidence in the SA. The SA um of the
blessed ones disciples they practice
well practiced uh straightforwardly
practice methodically and practice
masterfully. In other words, the four
types of noble disciples taken as pairs
eight when taken as individual types.
We'll address all these things
afterwards because the suit is quite
short. So uh there the s of the blessed
ones disciple worthy of gifts, worthy of
hospitality, worthy of offerings, worth
of respect and incomparable field of
merit for the world. And then um that
noble disciple is also endowed with
virtues that are appealing to the noble
ones, unto unbroken, unspotted,
unsputtered, liberating, praised by the
wise, untarnished, leading to
concentration or composure.
Uh suppose a tree was were leaning
towards the east, slanting towards the
east, inclining towards the east.
Uh when its root is cut, which way would
it fall? Well, it will fall whichever
way was leaning, slanting and inclining
Lord said Mahanama. In the same way,
Mahanama disciple of the noble ones when
endowed with four qualities leans
towards Nibbana, slants toward Nibbana
and inclines towards Nibbana.
So um so that
kind of concludes the the the reading of
the sutas. So as it can be seen from um
this is probably like one instance but
the Buddha gave numerous examples to
Mahanama and then he was remembered or
compilers would have divided it into
subsequent sutas and so on.
So as as it can be seen from the sutas
Mahanama was a noble disciple. So he was
at least a sautana
uh which means he has um understood the
dharma and the forable truths uh and
what the practice for complete sessation
of suffering is. So that's important to
kind of um recognize because um
it takes a bit more than just uh being a
good Buddhist so to speak like uh you
know every every every Buddhist today
would say yeah of course I have
confidence in the Buddha that he was the
greatest and I absolutely venerate the
SA they're the greatest disciples and
the dharma is perfectly expounded but u
these stock phrases from the sutas they
don't mean just a mere belief they're
basically like a condensed way of just
saying that his understanding of the
dharma would have verified his
confidence in the Buddha and any
subsequent disciple of the Buddha they
would be teaching the same. So in other
words he was a sautana with a internal
criteria to tell for himself uh what the
right dharma is and what isn't. So
obviously you know as as as we said so
many times before in the course of
history in the course of passing down
these um passing down these sutas and um
being memorized and then compiled
um pretty much all the nuances are gone
in that sense all the individual
variations. So now whenever somebody's a
sautana whenever somebody in whatever
idiosyncratic way might describe their
understanding of the principle of the
dharma well all we get is a stock stock
passage that says he has a verified
confidence in the Buddha uh the dharma
and the sanai and he's he's clear about
those things. So uh it's a bit more than
that than just being convinced that
those three things are the best three
holy trinity in the world to to to be uh
saved or to be safe from the perilous uh
rebirth. So
So
the only uh one that could be that can
say it's truly safe would be somebody
who's at least a sabban. So nothing
shorter than sapati guarantees safety
and that's mentioned in other sutas. So
that's why it's like a uh it's an
imperative for the practice. And
speaking now of sautapati actually I
mean the suta doesn't kind of me touch
upon that directly but it does sort of
raise a question. So Mahanama as a
sautapana didn't know what his how whether his
didn't know what his how whether his
rebirth will be good or bad. So somebody
today after reading all the sutras might
wonder about it. Well how's that
possible? Like so tapana is said so many
times that um they cannot go to bad
destination and they have seven seven
beings at most. So seven bas before they
will make an end to suffering. But u
actually in other sutas uh we get to see
how the whole idea of the four stages of
enlightenment came to be. Initially
there was there were no sautapanas.
There was no talk about sautapanas or
sakagamis or anagamis. It was uh those
who practice the dharma and those who
don't. Those who practice the dharma
would have been the ones who've seen the
dharma and then uh been on the way to
enlightenment. Um so it was like exactly
for those reasons when one of those
disciples died
um Ananda went to would go to the Buddha
and ask oh such and such passed away. Um
he was practicing the dharma he was
following your instruction. uh what was
his destination?
And then the Buddha would reply
uh well he was he was saved. He was
basically a non-returner. He would um he
would have been um he would have been
reborn in some higher heaven and he
would make an end to suffering. Then
somebody else died. It's like well he
would return one more time. And that has
been happening for quite a while. And at
one point when Ananda went to the Buddha
again with such a question, the Buddha
says, "Well, if whenever some disciple
of the target dies, you come and ask me
about the their destination, it's going
to be a bit of a hassle for me." And
it's becoming a bit of a hassle. So then
the Buddha formulated these external
criteria so that anybody who understands
the dharma um can then use that to infer
where other people's um people who were
passed away um are in terms of their
understanding of the dharma like uh in
terms of the practice sorry and also
they can use it to apply to themselves.
So uh as I said before there was no um
sorti or something. So it was just like
you either you're practicing the dharma
successfully or getting closer to it or
you're not or you're going in a
completely opposite direction or you're
not doing anything. So when the Buddha
outlined these four stages,
they are kind of like a like um um I
wouldn't say cornerstones, they're more
like a kind of um stations on the way.
again quite arbitrarily decided upon
certain say relevant uh aspects. So
sapat is relevant because obviously it's
the arising of the damay how the suta
say so it's the it's the it's the
understanding of what the path is what suffering is
of what the path is what suffering is
what the sessation of suffering is and
how to fully develop that sensation of
suffering. So it's kind of important. So
that's why it's like okay well that's
certainly one uh the one first station
as in like something that um cannot be
missed so to speak. Then the second one
sucked see that's already was quite
subjectively described as oh he weakened
the the other two fetas the fetter of
lust and aversion and in number of other
sutras it's completely omitted. The
Buddha would talk about sautapan and
then go and talk about anagami. So
sakilagami doesn't even occur because
again weakened at what level you don't
know. So it's more like a reference kind
of a guideline. Then obviously the third
anagami would be okay that's also
significant in a sense of it has like a
say a perceivable change. It's not just
weakening of certain uh fetterss but
it's abandonment of sensuality and ill
will which are obviously two major kind
of forces in the world. So u it would be
unmistaken equally unmistaken as the
rising of the damay and then obviously
aranchship uh would be sessation of all
the fetas and freedom from obviously all
of the als but even that there's so many
sutras where anagamis would have
overestimated themselves and thought
they were arans and the Buddha would say
oh yeah half of these monks they
declared arahantship they declared it
rightly but the other half they
overestimated themselves Not like that
they were wrong wrong in a sense but
it's just
the as the the remnants of the fetterss
that were left were so subtle that
nothing was coming up they were they
were practically free and that's why
even the Buddha himself often would talk
about somebody successfully practicing
the dharma to completion he would say
they would reach hardship here and now
or if there is some unspecified
residues left even he couldn't could not
necessarily tell always they would be
reborn in pure abboards as a non-
returnturn and never return from that
and then they will make an end of
suffering over there. So that's why it's
important like so even when it comes to
the first three fetas that sautapana is
free from um you need to you need to
realize it's it's the same practice. So
achieving sautapat is the same practice
that you do for aranchip. It's not like
oh I can practice for sautapana and aim
at these three fetas and not do the rest
of the noble path. So practice of dharma
is the practice of the noble ethal path
not uh fulfilling it completely you'll
be at least a sautapana or sakuragami or
anagami fulfilling it completely you'll
be an arand
because um the reason why insist on this
and and bring it up often is because
like it quite clearly says for example
the the right intention like well it
says that one cannot enter upon the
right path sautapati while practicing
the wrong path while not maintaining the
right path. And what is the right path?
Well, the right path is the right um
right recollection, right um intention.
Well, the noble path. And the point is
when it comes to right intention,
it's the intention of non-lust
uh non cruely, non-avversion. Those are
the right intentions.
So that's why even if somebody says oh
you know as a householder I can't
abandon my life because I have duties
and stuff so I can't practice for other
hardship and then on account of that they might
and then on account of that they might
feel excused from uh not restraining
sensuality and um and other kind of
aspects of the path that are deemed
later in practice but they're not from
the start in order to enter the the the
the rightful path as the suta says You
need to maintain these rightful aspects
of it. So you can't possibly be engaging
in sensuality, ill will, physically,
verbally, while somehow miraculously
having a mind of no intention towards
sensuality. That's that's that's
inconceivable. That's that's a
contradiction in terms and other sutras
do say that actually that one can engage
with sensuality without those
perceptions already being established
and perverted internally on the level of
that intention. That's impossible. So
that's why like uh Mahanama
or or any sortana doesn't need to know
about rebirths and and that whole thing
of seven bars that came from the Buddha
he formulated that and because people
had faith in him they okay took it but
it's not a measure of sapati whether you
see your next rebirth or something as a
matter of fact it's not a measure of
aranchip sar couldn't see anything in his own
sar couldn't see anything in his own
words um let alone other rebirths and
what's waiting for whom? But uh what is
the measure of sodati is that that that
first major as I said station that major
kind of um um
point which is the recognition of where
duka comes from what duka is like
completely unmistaken understanding of
what suffering is
which then obviously implicates
the the the the counterpart as well. So
if you clearly understand what suffering
is, you clearly understand what that
sessation of suffering is as well.
Um so then the whole noble path becomes
just like a an absolute thorough
fulfillment of that sessation of suffering
of that sessation of suffering
and that is what a sautan understands
that is what Mahanam understood. So
that's why like in this suta where where
he um
when he says his his mindfulness was
muddled and so on, it doesn't mean that
he became a puja
when he got scared. It just means that
that broader context of clarity was
somewhat obstructed because he obviously
hasn't fully trained his mind. So when
certain extreme situations come up they
would have u clouded as I said that that
the broadness of the context that he
would have otherwise been maintaining
but that's not to say that he would have
been fully overwhelmed gripped and
forgot where the actual dooka comes
from. That's inconceivable to forget
because obviously it's not a it's not
just on a level of information. It's not
like I learned yesterday dooka comes
from there and tomorrow somebody might
prove that wrong. No, it's it's
literally seeing the the the state of
mind like chitta nimita that animal we
talk about seeing suffering like
completely um inescapably
connected with that uh very craving of
that animal. So when animal is
exhibiting craving suffering is felt
regardless of the circumstances.
When animal is not exhibiting the
craving, there is no suffering felt whatsoever.
there is no suffering felt whatsoever.
And you see both clear as a day.
And that's exactly now. Okay. So, how do
I make the animal not crave noble path?
It's not a magical mystical meditation
um experience that suddenly sorted
everything out. No, it's a recognition
through obviously already having certain
recognitions of where that animal is,
where your state of mind is, what your
chitter is. But it's then recognition of
okay so it needs to be an absolute
thorough complete training of this
entity of this chitta so that it becomes
incapable of craving even traces of it
then I will become incapable of
suffering as simple as that as
straightforward as that but that's not
to say it's easy obviously so Mahanama
could not have doubted that because as I
said sodapat is not measured by
knowledge of your eberts aranchip is not
measured by that um it was just an
external criteria that can be used
skillfully like like in this case you
know he was he he wasn't like
necessarily as I said over overwhelmed
by suffering or gripped but as he he
admits oh his perspective diminished and
he thought if I were to die now
would that matter where would I go where
would I be reborn
so it's a kind of reassurance coming
from the Buddha himself uh that well
don't worry about it because really what
matters is what you've been doing up to
that point. Have you been training your
chitter correctly? Have you becoming a
consumate established in virtue? How the
suta says in discernment, in composure,
in being able to endure things on the
right level? Have you been doing that
most of the time? If yes, you don't have
to worry about the last moment of your
death and so on. Even even if the
perspective diminishes there and then
because it's well as the simile is
explained it's like if the tree has been
growing in one direction doesn't matter
how you cut it
from what angle you come it's going to
fall in that direction because it's
already heavily slanted and that's
exactly the point to incline the mind
towards nibbana. The more you do so, the
better it will be. So then doesn't
matter from what angle the death comes
and whether you're prepared for it or
not. Uh whether you're anticipating it
or not, it will go that way.
So So that's why the the the um the four
stages of enlightenment are kind of just
like an external guideline
um that you can use to review a mind, to
review a state. But fundamentally uh the
practice in and of itself is the
practice towards that noble path towards
the purification through virtue uh sense
restraint and taming of that animal and
that's as we described in other um in
other talks on base of other sutras
that's the practice for puja as well.
So, Vutua needs to uh do pretty much try
and emulate as as as perfectly as
possible the practice of dharma which is
the practice of the noble path which can
then enable them to actually get the
sense of what the chitta is, what that
entity is
then everything else obviously that
depends on that can begin to grow.
So um
yeah so I think we addressed this like
if if such knowledge um of rebirths
is not available
how can one know for sure without doubt
that thereat or not I just answered that
in there yeah and um yeah so obviously I
also addressed the the very common view
that and that's obviously very common in
the in certainly in the Buddhist
cultures that it's the um uh what you
think what your last thought is at the
moment of death that's what determines
your rebirth and obviously these both
sutas show that as completely wrong
uh because not just that um well not
just that it doesn't make sense like if
you think about it it's like so what you
can practice the whole life but then
have one weird thought at the end of the
life like mahanama perspective maybe
shrunk a bit and that will completely
send you the other way. That um doesn't
make sense in that way. But it also you
realize the reason why people would kind
of almost prefer that type of view is
because it's you know it allows for a a
great deal of wishful thinking that
you're going to have the right thought
because you're such a faithful Buddhist
and also uh completely to not feel
responsible for everything you're doing
in the meantime while you're alive
for not planting that tree while you
still can. and then I'll just have a
magical right thought of right faith and
and so on unshakable faith when I'm
dying it's like yeah sure um what are
the chances of that and even if you do
by the way even if you cut the tree so
imagine how the tree is slanting away
from nibbana not towards it
and your last thought is the absolutely
perfect thought but mind you your whole
life preceding that was absolutely
unrestrained opposite of the noble aful
path So even if your last thought was
So even if your last thought was
perfect, that could be say the
absolutely perfect angle, perfect wedge
cut on a tree, uh perfect notch,
everything. Do you think that tree still wouldn't
Do you think that tree still wouldn't
fall in the direction that's heavily
slanted? No, it would. So your perfect
thought would not make a difference if
your life was not being led according to
the principles that the Buddha
described, principles of training. So
it kind of clearly shows it's just on a
level of of wishful thinking and almost
kind of mystified um ideas of rebirth uh
that conveniently as I said would be
taking away or feeling you're not so
responsible for stuff you do like on a
dayto-day basis.
So I actually got a question regarding
the second suta. Um
like one of the things that's often
recommended for householders
are the six anusatis
like recollection of Buddha dhamama
sanga u virtue and so on and so forth. So I
u virtue and so on and so forth. So I
was wondering similarly to that you said
that you can imitate or try to emulate
the noble eightful path.
>> How should a pujana emulate the first
three recollections like Buddha Damasa
which then
Yeah. Well, again, it's not it's not the
recollection of the actual
images or statues or whatever you think
the Buddha looked like.
It's a recollection of the values.
So, when you think the Buddha, do you
think sexual intercourse?
When you think the Buddha, do you think
punching somebody in the face?
Do you think s when you think sa you see
group of people? Do you think uh
backstabbing, gossip, lying, stealing,
malations? No. That's what it means to
recollect the Buddha, Dhamma, and Sana.
Not light cheap in about 108 times to a
shrine and think about fantasy and your
imaginary friends. No, actually
recollect the values. When you think
Buddha, what does that stand for?
And now contrast your behavior to that.
contrast your planning uh future
behavior to that things that you're
planning to do.
So it's like yeah it's an actual
recollection of the right suitable
uh uh useful wholesome contexts
that obviously go hand in hand with
virtue and that sense restraint and
right composure.
So that's what it means to recollect
these things and actually the Buddha did
say that for a noble disciple household
a noble disciple who who frequently
recollects the Buddha Damasa and the
unbroken virtue um they have the
pleasant abiding here and now like same
description like for Janna the pleasant
abiding here and now
because that's where composure comes
from that's where peace and the
recognition of the existing happiness
comes
So in a way any any recollection that
one does should always be concerning
one's actions, one's current way of
being. >> Exactly. Exactly. So any recollection
>> Exactly. Exactly. So any recollection
that one does should be inherently based
on the values that one is contrasting to
the current actions previous actions the
ones you're planning to do the current
uh the current not not like oh think
about as I said think about the eighth
factor of patada or something when that
car carries no value it might for
somebody who would have thought about it
long enough and practiced rightly it
might carry the value of simultaneity
and sense restraint and and disp
passion. But for more people, certainly
in the beginning, it won't.
It's just going to be an abstract theory
that you're going to convince yourself
you're thinking about the dharma while
you're actually not. While your
experience is still having unchecked
passion, unchecked ill will, unchecked
hindrances. So it's always needs to come down onto
So it's always needs to come down onto
the level of actions. So when you think
about the Buddha Damasa, as I said,
those stock phrases, you think about the
values that are now being compared to
your currently maintained values to
things you're doing, things you're
planning to do.
>> And the the pleasant abiding here now
would be a product of realizing
I'm actually I'm in line with that.
>> Yes. Yes. So it would be the result of
realizing that you're aligned with that
or if you were not of aligning yourself
with that because that's the thing. If
you are uh recollecting these values
contrasted against your actions, recent
actions, the ones you're planning to do,
the choice becomes very clear. Your
choice becomes clear.
Do I follow what I clearly know
is aligned with uh the Buddha, the
dharma, the sana, or do I don't follow
that? No, no external excuses or reason
necessary. Oh, well, but I'm a household
and no, no, no. All that comes second.
Right there. And then, you have a clear
choice. There is a value of the noble
ethal path, as I said, and the value
opposite of that. I can't do both. And I
have a choice. If I give this up, I'm
choosing the noble ethal path. And
tomorrow, I might have to do the same
and the day after I have to do the same.
But right there and then the choice that
arises is very clear and it's felt.
And then you realize, okay, so what's
stopping me from choosing the the right
practice? What's stopping me from
choosing the noble path? Oh, me not
choosing it. That's what's stopping me
every single time. Nothing else can come
in between. No wife, no kids, nothing
can come in between.
No duties, no business, no family, no
other monasteries, other monks, nothing
can come between.
It's yours and yours only.